<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE properties SYSTEM "http://java.sun.com/dtd/properties.dtd">
<properties>
  <entry key="shortInfo">Basic Docmenta HTML Checks</entry>
  <entry key="trim_empty_paras.title">Checks if content node ends with an empty paragraph</entry>
  <entry key="trim_figure_spaces.title">Checks for whitespace around figures</entry>
  <entry key="msgEmptyParaExists">Found an empty paragraph at the end of the content node.</entry>
  <entry key="msgEmptyParaRemoved">Removed empty paragraph from the end of the content node.</entry>
  <entry key="msgFigureSpacesExist">Found whitespace around figure.</entry>
  <entry key="msgFigureSpacesRemoved">Removed whitespace around figure.</entry>
  <entry key="longInfo"><![CDATA[
  <p>
  This class provides basic Docmenta HTML checks. Following a detailed description of the 
  supported arguments and checks.  
  check:
  </p>
  <big><b>Arguments:</b></big>
  <p><em>none</em></p>
  <big><b>Checks:</b></big>
  <dl>
    <dt><b>trim_empty_paras</b></dt>
    <dd>
        <p>
        This check searches for an empty paragraph at the end of content nodes. 
        If auto-correction is enabled, then an empty paragraph at the end of a content
        node is removed.
        </p>
        <p>
        This check can be useful, because some WYSIWYG editors append an empty 
        paragraph, if the cursor is placed at the end of the content.
        </p>
        <p>
        Following HTML fragments are recognized as empty paragraphs:
        </p>
        <pre>
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;/p&gt;</pre>
        </p>
    </dd>

    <dt><b>trim_figure_spaces</b></dt>
    <dd>
        <p>
        This check searches for whitespace around figures.
        If auto-correction is enabled, then the whitespace is removed.
        </p>
        <p>
        A figure is cosidered to be an HTML <tt>img</tt> element that has
        a <tt>title</tt> attribute assigned. In Docmenta, figures should be
        placed as a single element inside of paragraphs, 
        as shown by the following HTML fragment: 
        <pre>
          &lt;p&gt;<lt;img title="..." ... /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</pre>
        <p>
        No whitespace should exist between the <tt>img</tt> and the 
        <tt>p</tt> tags.
        However, if the content is created by a WYSIWYG editor, then
        whitespace is not visible and may be inserted by mistake.
        This check can be used to automatically remove such whitespace.
        </p>
        <p>
        Note that besides spaces, tabs and line breaks, this check also
        recognizes the character entities &amp;nbsp; and &amp;#160; as 
        whitespace.
        </p>
    </dd>

  </dl>

  ]]>
  </entry>    
</properties>
