<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE properties SYSTEM "http://java.sun.com/dtd/properties.dtd">
<properties>
  <entry key="shortInfo">Apply styles to even and odd lines and optionally add line numbers.</entry>
  <entry key="longInfo"><![CDATA[
  <big><b>Arguments:</b></big>
  <dl>
    <dt><b><tt>start=[<i>INTEGER</i>|off]</tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The line-numbering start value. Set to an integer value to enable line numbering.
    Set to <tt>off</tt>, to disable line numbering. Default is <tt>off</tt>.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>line=<i>STYLE_ID</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The default block-style to be assigned to lines.
    If no default style is specified, and no other style defined by the arguments
    <tt>odd</tt>, <tt>even</tt> or <tt>mstyle</tt> is appropriate then no style
    is assigned to the line.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>odd=<i>STYLE_ID</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The block-style to be assigned to odd lines.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>even=<i>STYLE_ID</i></tt></b>:
    <dd>The block-style to be assigned to even lines.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>num=<i>STYLE_ID</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The default block-style to be assigned to line-numbers.
    If no default style is specified, and no other style defined by the arguments
    <tt>onum</tt>, <tt>enum</tt> or <tt>mnum</tt> is appropriate, then the same
    style is assigned to the line-number as to the the line-content.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>onum=<i>STYLE_ID</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The block-style to be assigned to odd line-numbers.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>enum=<i>STYLE_ID</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The block-style to be assigned to even line-numbers.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>cbox=<i>STYLE_ID</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>Content-box style. The ID of the block-style to be assigned to the content-block.
    If <tt>cbox</tt> is not set, then the original style of the input-element is assigned.
    Note that if line-numbering is enabled, then this box does <em>not</em>
    include the line-numbers.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>nbox=<i>STYLE_ID</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>Numbering-box style. If line-numbering is enabled, this block-style is
    assigned to the box which encloses all line-numbers. If not specified,
    then no style is assigned.
    If line-numbering is disabled, then this setting has no effect.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>box=<i>STYLE_ID</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>Outer-box style. If line-numbering is enabled, this block-style is
    assigned to the outer-box which encloses the content and the line-numbers.
    If not specified, then no style is assigned to the outer-box.
    If line-numbering is disabled, then this setting has no effect.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>keep=[auto|always]</tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The page break behaviour. Set to <tt>auto</tt>, to allow page breaks
    within the result-block. Set to <tt>always</tt>, to prevent page breaks
    within the result-block. Default is <tt>always</tt>.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>nw=<i>WIDTH</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The horizontal space that is reserved for the line-numbers.
    If not specified, then the default width of <tt>32pt</tt> is used.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>maxcols=<i>INTEGER</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The maximum number of characters per line.
    If the maximum number of characters is reached, then an automatic line-break
    is inserted. Automatically inserted line-breaks do not increase the line-number.
    Set to 0, to disable automatic line-breaks. Default is 0 (disabled).</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>lbc=[<i>CHARACTER</i>]</tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The automatic line-break character. If an automatic line break is inserted
    due to the <tt>maxcols</tt> argument, then <i>CHARACTER</i> is inserted at
    the end of the broken line to indicate that the line is continued on the next line.
    If not specified or set to empty string, then no line-break character is inserted.
    <i>CHARACTER</i> has to be a single character or a character entity,
    e.g. "<tt>&amp;#8230;</tt>".</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>pre=[true|false]</tt></b></dt>
    <dd>Indication whether input is preformatted or not. If set to <tt>true</tt>,
    line-break characters in the XHTML source
    cause line breaks in the rendered output. Otherwise only &lt;br /&gt;
    elements are rendered as line breaks. Default is <tt>false</tt>.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>tab=<i>INTEGER</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The tab size. If the specified integer value is positive, then tab
    characters are transformed to the number of spaces given by this value.
    If the integer value is 0 or the argument is missing, then tab
    characters are <em>not</em> transformed.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>m=<i>PATTERN</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The marker pattern. If a line contains the character sequence
    <i>PATTERN</i>, then the line is highlighted with the styles given by the
    arguments <tt>mstyle</tt> and <tt>mnum</tt>.
    If not specified, then highlighting is disabled.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>mstyle=<i>STYLE_ID</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The ID of the block-style to be assigned to marked lines.
    If not specified, then no style is assigned to marked lines.</dd>

    <dt><b><tt>mnum=<i>STYLE_ID</i></tt></b></dt>
    <dd>The ID of the block-style to be assigned to the line numbers of marked lines.
    If not specified, then no style is assigned to the line-numbers of marked lines.</dd>
  </dl>
  <p><big><b>Notes:</b></big></p>
  <p>
    If the arguments <tt>onum</tt> and/or <tt>enum</tt> are provided, then
    the specified styles should have the same margin, padding and font-size values
    as the styles specified for the arguments <tt>line</tt>, <tt>odd</tt> and <tt>even</tt>.
    Otherwise the line-numbers may not be in line with the corresponding 
    lines of the content.
  </p>
  <p>
    Setting the argument <tt>maxcols</tt> to a positive value only makes sense
    for preformatted text which is rendered with a fixed-width font
    (i.e. the line style should include the CSS properties
    <tt>font-family: monospace</tt> and <tt>white-space: pre</tt>).
  </p>
  <p><big><b>Inline arguments:</b></big></p>
  <p>
    Besides setting the arguments in the Auto-Format style defintion (see examples below),
    the arguments can also be set as first line of the input-element.
    For this, the first line must be provided in the format
    <tt>[args:&nbsp;<i>arg1=value1&nbsp;arg2=value2&nbsp;...</i>&nbsp;]</tt>.
    If the same argument is set in the Auto-Format style definition and
    in the first line of the input, then the later takes precedence.
    For example, following input-element sets the line-numbering start value to 3,
    overwriting any start value that was set in the Auto-Format configuration of the style
    <tt>listing</tt>:
  </p>
  <pre>
    &lt;div class="listing"&gt;
      [args: start=3]&lt;br/&gt;
      Line 1&lt;br/&gt;
      Line 2&lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;  </pre>
  <p><big><b>Referencing lines:</b></big></p>
  <p>
    If a line contains an inline-element, i.e. contains text thas was formatted with an
    inline-style, and the inline-element has an <tt>id</tt>-attribute assigned,
    but no <tt>title</tt>-attribute, then the <tt>title</tt>-attribute is set to the
    line-number. This way it is possible, to create references to
    inline-elements, where the link text is automatically replaced by the line
    number of the referenced element (i.e. you can create text like
    "<tt>see line x</tt>"), where <tt>x</tt> is a link whose link-text is replaced
    during export by the line-number.
  </p>
  <p>
    An alternative way of referencing lines, is to mark the line and attach an
    ID to the marker. The marker pattern is defined by the argument
    <tt>m=<i>PATTERN</i></tt> (see description of the arguments above). To attach
    an ID to a marker, put the ID in square brackets after the marker.
    For example, if you have set the argument <tt>m=###</tt>, then you can
    mark a line and assign the ID <tt>line_a</tt> to it, by placing
    the substring "<tt>###[line_a]</tt>" somewhere within the line.
  </p>
  <p>
    Be aware that an ID has to start with a letter or underscore and must only
    contain letters, digits, underscores or dashes.
  </p>
  <p><big><b>Examples:</b></big></p>
  <p>
    Following Auto-Format style configuration transforms the input into a formatted
    listing with line-numbers, where the style <tt>line_style</tt> is applied to
    lines. The line-numbering starts with 1.
    A horizontal space of 28pt is reserved for the line-numbers.
    Furthermore the content and the line-numbers are enclosed in a box with 
    style <tt>listing_frame</tt>.
  </p>
  <pre>
    org.docma.plugin.examples.FormatLines start=1 line=line_style nw=28pt box=listing_frame </pre>
  <p>
    Following configuration transforms the input into a formatted listing without
    line-numbers. The character sequence '###' can be used to
    mark lines. Marked lines are highlighted with style <tt>red_line</tt>.
    Page breaks are allowed within the listing.
  </p>
  <pre>
    org.docma.plugin.examples.FormatLines start=off m=### mstyle=red_line keep=auto
  </pre>
    ]]>
  </entry>
</properties>
